<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The information of William Lewis, Gent, delivered at the bar of the House of Commons, the eighteenth of November, 1680 together with his further narrative relating thereto : in all which is contained a confirmation of the popish plot and the justice of the executions done upon Grove, Pickering, and the</title>
            <author>Lewis, William, Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48296</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12408973</idno>
  <idno type="VID">61458</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240948917</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21973</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12408973</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 282:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The information of William Lewis, Gent, delivered at the bar of the House of Commons, the eighteenth of November, 1680 together with his further narrative relating thereto : in all which is contained a confirmation of the popish plot and the justice of the executions done upon Grove, Pickering, and the</title>
                  <author>Lewis, William, Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:61458:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jovis die Novembris 18. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Ordered,</p>
            <p>THat Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> have leave of this House to Print his Information this day given in at the Bar of this House.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>William Goldsbrough,</hi>
                  <lb/> Cler. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>BY vertue of this Order above-ment<gap reason="illegible: page creased" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I do appoint <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near Stationers-Hall, to Print my Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that no other Person or Persons do Print the same.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Lewis.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 6. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61458:1"/>
            <p>THE INFORMATION OF William Lewis, <hi>GENT.</hi> Delivered at the BAR of <hi>The House of Commons,</hi> The Eighteenth of <hi>November,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>Together with His further NARRATIVE relating thereto.</p>
            <p>In all which is contained A Confirmation of the POPISH PLOT, and the Justice of the Executions done upon <hi>Grove, Pickering,</hi> and the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites for the Design of Killing His Most Sacred Majesty.</p>
            <p>And discovering further the Design of the Papists to set the Navy Royal on Fire in Harbour; and to throw the guilt of the whole upon the Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>With their Contrivances to take away the Life of the Right Honourable <hi>Anthony</hi> Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near Stationers-Hall, MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:61458:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61458:2"/>
            <head>THE DEPOSITIONS OF Mr. William Lewis.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>BOUT <hi>February,</hi> in the Year 1677, being then resident in <hi>London,</hi> and out of Employment, I went to one <hi>Walter Jones</hi> a Priest, formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Wild-House,</hi> being a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son with whom I had been acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from my Childhood, desiring him to help me to some Employment. An Army being then upon raising for <hi>Flanders,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> went with me to one <hi>Grove,</hi> since Executed for Treasons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Plot, but then living at the <hi>Golden-Ball</hi> in <hi>York-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> At whose House, after some little discourse, the said <hi>Grove</hi> appointed Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> and my self to go to the <hi>Wind-Mill</hi> Tavern in <hi>Bridges-street,</hi> in the aforesaid Parish, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to come to us, which he accordingly did. There Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> acquaints <hi>Grove</hi> that I was his particular Friend, and a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, and that he knew a great many of my Relations, who likewise were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, and how at that juncture of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61458:3"/> time I wanted an Employment, desiring him to lay out for one as much as in him lay. To which <hi>Grove</hi> replyed, that he would do for me as much as lay in his power, desiring me to call upon him at his House, and put him in mind of his promise. Which accordingly I did several times. The chief of our Discourse was still concerning the then present Estate of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in <hi>England,</hi> and he would be often wishing that that Religion might be well established in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After about four Months acquaintance with <hi>Grove,</hi> the aforesaid Mr. <hi>Walter Jones</hi> came to see me; I then acquainted him I had not been at Confession a long time; Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> advised me to go to Father <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court,</hi> (since Executed for Treason,) to <hi>Groves</hi> House, where Mass was commonly said.</p>
            <p>In or about the Month of <hi>May</hi> 1678. I went to <hi>Groves</hi> House, with Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> where there was an Altar set up in a Room one pair of Stairs. There I was Confessed by the said <hi>Harcourt;</hi> and as we were just going to Mass, <hi>Grove</hi> took an occasion to speak to me, (<hi>Whitebread, Harcourt, Fenwick,</hi> since Executed for the same Treasons, and all the rest of the Company looking another way, as not seeming to take any notice of the discourse between <hi>Grove</hi> and my self,) and in that discourse this Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation past between us. <hi>Grove</hi> said to me, that if I would be ruled by him, I should be made for ever. I replyed I would submit my self to him. Then <hi>Grove</hi> took up a Pistol which lay on the left side of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar saying, <hi>This is that which must do the business,</hi> or words to that effect, <hi>but I will not reveal it to you, till you have taken the Sacrament to be secret;</hi> which I did upon his Request, at the same time with <hi>Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61458:3"/> and himself, <hi>Harcourt</hi> being the Person who Administred. After Mass was ended, and the Altar removed, (for that was the usual custom in that place,) all the Company sat down at the Table in the Room, and I among the rest. Then <hi>Grove</hi> said, the business is to kill the King. To which I made answer, How! to kill the King! for what? Then <hi>Grove</hi> and most of the Company said, <hi>The King is a</hi> Heretick, <hi>and it is no Sin to kill him, or any other, to propagate the Roman Catholick Religion.</hi> They asked me, whether I knew the Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Peters?</hi> I answer'd, yes: Then <hi>Grove,</hi> scratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Head, seemed to be somewhat concern'd, and askt me again, whether I knew the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> and Lord <hi>Bellasis?</hi> I answered, I did not. Then most of the Company told me, if I would venture as far as <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Grove,</hi> I should have at least one thousand pounds for a Reward, and that some of the best persons in <hi>England</hi> would engage their Honours for the true payment of the Money to me, after the business was effected; and that I should be safely conveyed either into <hi>France,</hi> or where I pleased; or if I would choose to tarry in <hi>England, I</hi> should have a Commission in the Catholick Army, which in a short time should be raised; with much more discourse to that effect.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>Jones</hi> and <hi>I</hi> took our leaves, <hi>Grove</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring us to call upon him the next day (as <hi>I</hi> take it) which we did, and went with him from his House to the <hi>Plough-Alehouse,</hi> near <hi>Somerset-House</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> where we found <hi>Harcourt, Pickering,</hi> and five or six more. At that Meeting <hi>Grove</hi> urged the business to me very home. <hi>I</hi> replyed, <hi>I</hi> had bought a Horse, and was to go into the Lord of <hi>Oxford</hi>'s Guard, which <hi>I</hi> lookt upon as a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61458:4"/> so that now, said <hi>I,</hi> should <hi>I</hi> go with you, and miscarry, <hi>I</hi> should be ruin'd. To which <hi>Grove</hi> replyed, Fear it not: and then the rest seconded him, and directing their speech to me, said, <hi>Grove</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> shall go with you. <hi>I</hi> told them <hi>I</hi> had nothing but their bare words for my Gratuity. Whereupon <hi>Grove</hi> drew out of his Pocket a pair of Beads and a Manual Book, and solemnly vowed, holding them in his hands, That one of the best Persons in <hi>England</hi> should ingage himself for what was promised me. As to that, <hi>I</hi> told them, they might bring me a person <hi>I</hi> knew not, who might probably be no such person of Quality as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Then <hi>Grove,</hi> holding his Beads and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual in his hands, as aforesaid, vowed it should be a Person of Quality; and desired me to meet him the next morning between nine or ten of the clock at <hi>Somerset-House</hi>-Chappel, but if the Chappel Doors were not open, that I should walk by the Coach-Houses, and he would be certainly there.</p>
            <p>Thus we parted, and the next morning I went, and met <hi>Grove,</hi> as he had appointed; who told me, that the Person of Quality could not then come, but wish'd me to meet him at four of the Clock that Afternoon, assuring me that the person of Quality would be there at that time. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly I did; and then <hi>Grove</hi> brought me into <hi>Somerset-House</hi> Garden, where were also <hi>Harcourt, Fenwick, Pickering,</hi> and some four or five more.</p>
            <p>About two Hours after my first coming into the Garden, there came a Person of Quality, who asked which was the man? Then <hi>Grove</hi> pointed to me, standing then under the <hi>Piazza,</hi> or Arched place in the said Garden, upon which the said Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61458:4"/> of Quality took me by the hand, and led me away a part from the rest of the Company, and then began to speak to me in these following words, or to this effect: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am sensible you know what you are to do. I answered, my Lord, what am I to do? His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship said, You are to go with <hi>Grove</hi> to Assassinate the King, and you shall have, when the business is effected, fifteen hundred pounds upon my Honour for a Reward; and if you like tarrying in <hi>England,</hi> you shall have a Commission in the Catholick Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which will be suddenly raised; or you shall safely be conveyed into <hi>France,</hi> or where you please.</p>
            <p>His Lordship gave me a Guinny, and bid me be rul'd by <hi>Grove,</hi> and so went away. Now <hi>Grove</hi> and the rest, had informed me before, that that same Person of Quality who should be ingaged for my Reward, was to be the Lord <hi>Bellasis:</hi> But I found it to be the Lord <hi>Arundel.</hi> When I was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by the House of Lords, concerning this matter, their Lordships asked me what Lord <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> I meant? I answer'd their Lordships, I knew him not by his Title. Then being asked what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Person the said Lord was? I Replyed, he was Squint-Eyed, and had a kind of a Wart upon his Nose.</p>
            <p>When the said Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> was gone from the place where he spoke to me in <hi>Somerset-House</hi>-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Grove</hi> asked me if I was satisfied? <hi>I</hi> said yes, and withal repeated to <hi>Grove,</hi> and the rest, what the Lord had said to me; not taking notice in the least, but that it was the same Person they had menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to me, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord <hi>Bellasis. Harcourt</hi> told me, if <hi>I</hi> would not be contented to stay in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61458:5"/> after the business was effected, <hi>I</hi> should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to <hi>France,</hi> or elsewhere, or to <hi>Florence,</hi> where the said Lord had great interest.</p>
            <p>After some more discourse of this Nature, we parted, and in some short time after that, <hi>I</hi> went with <hi>Jones</hi> to the <hi>Plough-Alehouse,</hi> where <hi>Whitebread, Harcourt,</hi> and five or six more were met, at which time there was in their Company a tall, lusty <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish</hi>-Man, black Hair'd; who, as <hi>I</hi> understood after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, was to be imployed to kill some Person of Quality; but the main of our discourse then was concerning the Number of <hi>Prosselites</hi> they had Converted, since the first time the last Toleration for Liberty of Conscience had been granted; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing their sorrow for it's being repeal'd, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless they doubted not, but very suddenly to have more freedom in <hi>England</hi> than ever they had since Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days; much applauding Father <hi>Patrick</hi> for being a main instrument in bringing over the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to the Catholicks.</p>
            <p>Another time <hi>I</hi> went with the said <hi>Jones</hi> to the aforesaid <hi>Plough-Alehouse,</hi> where was <hi>Harcourt, White-bread,</hi> and one <hi>Kelly</hi> a Priest, as <hi>Jones</hi> told me, and the tall black <hi>Irish</hi>-man, with three or four more, whose Names <hi>I</hi> cannot remember, but believe <hi>I</hi> should remember their Faces if <hi>I</hi> saw them. The substance of their discourse was, that if some Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were not suddenly removed, it would prove very detrimental to the business, giving some hint of a faint-hearted Person, whom they had imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but feared he would not effect his work. Thereupon as if it had been to supply that defect, they asked me if I would be imployed? To which I readily gave my Compliance, as being thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to before-hand desired by <hi>Jones,</hi> believing as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61458:5"/> that it might be an incouragement to the aforesaid Lusty <hi>Irish</hi>-Man to do the same, and at the same time repeating their former Position, and alledging that it was no sin to kill any Heretick to propagate the Catholick Cause.</p>
            <p>This strange discourse being over, we agreed to meet again the next Morning, at the <hi>White-Horse-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and so we parted. Neither did I go the next day to meet them at the <hi>White-Horse</hi> according to my promise. For being much troubled in Conscience, for such a voluntary Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of my self to secresie, by taking the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not knowing what it was I was to do, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I had taken it, I presently resolv'd not to have any further Conferences with those People, but sold my Horse, and went to <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I thus was gone from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Oxford,</hi> I chang'd my Name, and went by the Name of <hi>Winter,</hi> for fear of being pursued by the Malice of the Complotters, for declining their Proposals; and not only so, but I also desired my Acquaintance that they would know me by no other Name than that of <hi>Winter,</hi> for Reasons best known to my self.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Oxford</hi> I went to <hi>Bristol,</hi> and in about eight Weeks after my first departure from <hi>London,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd again, and soon after that the Plot was detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But before that, I well remember, I saw <hi>Grove</hi> come out of the House where Captain <hi>Lavalline</hi> lay in <hi>Leicester-Fields,</hi> and I asked <hi>Grove</hi> where he had been? who reply'd, he had been with the said Captain <hi>Lavalline,</hi> but did not tell me his business. <hi>I</hi> have also seen Captain <hi>Lavalline</hi> once or twice go into <hi>Groves</hi> House.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61458:6"/>
            <p>After my return to <hi>London,</hi> I became intimately acquainted with one <hi>Richard Thomson,</hi> who lived over against <hi>Somerset-House,</hi> being one that sold <hi>Beads</hi> and Popish <hi>Books,</hi> and was for villyfying of Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> committed to the <hi>Gate-House</hi>-Prison in <hi>Westminster. I</hi> found by the said <hi>Thomsons</hi> discourse, that he believed there was no Plot, and much desired to have the Kings Evidence blasted. Whereupon <hi>I</hi> proposed to him a way whereby Captain <hi>Bedlows</hi> Evidence might be rendred invalid. This design presently took with him, and therefore he desired me to draw up in writing what I had to propose; saying, he would send it to some of the best Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in <hi>England</hi> to peruse, and that if it were liked by them, I should not want incouragement to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Accordingly I drew up my design in Paper, and he sent it by one of his Daughters to another Daughter of his living at the Lord <hi>Bellasis</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment in the <hi>Tower;</hi> and this was the substance of the said Paper, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will go to <hi>Bedlow,</hi> with whom I was formerly intimately acquainted, and I will make him believe that I was one at the killing of Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury-Godfry,</hi> and that I would become an Evidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to Corroborate his. Provided Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> would first upon Oath accuse me to be one that was actual at the said Murther; which if he would do, I would retract my former promises, and produce Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to prove my self to be in another place both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, at, and after the time of the said Murther. This Paper being delivered by means of the conveyance already mentioned, the said <hi>Thomsons</hi> Daughter brought her Father word, that the said Paper was sent to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> directing him to go to St. <hi>James</hi>'s-<hi>Court</hi> for an Answer, to one Mrs. <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liots</hi> the Dukes Nurse, as <hi>Thomson</hi> told me himself. I saw him go in to the said S. <hi>James</hi>'s-<hi>House,</hi> and tarryed for him, according to his appointment in the <hi>Pall-Mall</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61458:6"/> whither in some short time he returned, and gave me five Guineys, desiring me to proceed with all care and diligence, saying; <hi>If I could effect what I had proposed, I should never want; for he that sent me the five Guineys, would be the best friend to me of any man in</hi> England: I asked him who sent them? He answered, <hi>No less man than His Royal Highness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Order to the effecting of the said Proposal, I went in some short time after, with a Resolution to give Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> a visit, who then hapned not to be within. Whereupon I returned to the said <hi>Thompson,</hi> who was then in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> with one <hi>Nevill, alias Paine,</hi> who was privy to the business. I told them Captain <hi>Bedlow</hi> was not within; upon which it was resolved, that I should make enquiry in all places we could imagin where Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> had lodged, with an intention, by that means, to find out whither he had not been in <hi>England,</hi> when he sware himself to be in <hi>Flanders,</hi> about carrying on the Plot. With this Design I went accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to several places where I thought he had lodged, and likewise to several Prisons, but could not find any thing material, until I went to the <hi>King's-Bench</hi> Prison, where I found that one of the Name, and a <hi>Welsh-man,</hi> had been there a Prisoner, and by all description I did verily believe him to have been the same Captain <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</hi> For that reason I took a copy of his Causes, and went immediately to the said <hi>Thompson,</hi> and made him acquainted with what I had done: And indeed we thought we had made a great progress; for that having perused a Narrative of <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal, we found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, That the said Captain <hi>Bedlow</hi> had sworn how he had been with Father <hi>Harcourt,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi>'s House, where he received a Packer of Letters, as I take it, in <hi>May</hi> the 24th or 25th, 1677. to carry into <hi>Flanders,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61458:7"/> and in the said Copy of Causes, we found he had been a close Prisoner at the same time, in the aforesaid Prison of <hi>King's-Bench.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thompson</hi> was so transported with the good News, as we then took it to be, That he went immediately to St. <hi>James</hi>'s Court, and delivered the said Copy of the Causes, inclosed in a Letter of mine (directed to him) to the said Madam <hi>Elliott,</hi> as he himself told me. Which having done, he returned to me to the usual place, in the <hi>Pall-Mall,</hi> where he appointed me to tarry for him; and from thence we immediately went to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> upon his saying, <hi>That</hi> Madam Elliot <hi>had appointed him so to do.</hi> Being got to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> we went into the <hi>Stone-Gallery</hi> in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where I saw a pretty lusty elderly Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man speak to the said <hi>Thompson,</hi> which Gentlewoman I understood afterwards by him the said <hi>Thompson,</hi> to be the said <hi>Madam Elliot,</hi> who ordered him to tarry till she came down (for she went up to the Duke's Appartments.) In about half an hours time she returned, bidding him carry the said Letter to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> the Duke having kept a Copy of the Causes. All which I had from <hi>Thompson</hi>'s own mouth.</p>
            <p>This was on the night before the Dissolution of the first Parliament. Posting from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> we went to <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> Fields, to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi>'s House, and there <hi>Thompson</hi> delivered the said Letter to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> herself, who ordered him the said <hi>Thompson,</hi> to call the next day for an Answer, as he said, for that she the said Lady <hi>Powis</hi> would first acquaint the Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> concerning the business, which was at large mentioned in my said Letter. <hi>Thompson</hi> went according to that Order to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> the next day, and returned in a short time to me. But I found by the event that some
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61458:7"/> others had been to enquire at the <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> where it appeared upon a more strict Enquiry, that it was not Captain <hi>Bedlow,</hi> but that it was his Brother, who had been then a Prisoner at the time mentioned in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Copy of Causes. By which mistake of mine I was laid aside, and looked upon as one that had a design upon them.</p>
            <p>About the time the five Jesuits were executed, I went with one <hi>Theophilus Dalton,</hi> an <hi>Irish</hi> Gentleman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one Squire <hi>Loftus,</hi> to <hi>Knightsbridge,</hi> to visit one who went by the Name of <hi>Churchill,</hi> and there sheltered himself under the Notion of a Dr. of <hi>Physick,</hi> but really was a <hi>Priest.</hi> With him I had some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course concerning what I proposed to <hi>Thompson,</hi> relating to Captain <hi>Bedlow.</hi> Upon which he desired me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him what it was, and if he liked it, he would send or go himself to the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> from whom I should have incouragement to proceed. I told him, it was then too long to Rehearse, in regard it was late. However, at his Request, I promised to wait on him next morning, and accordingly I went to his Lodging in <hi>Knightsbridge,</hi> at a <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> House at the Sign of the Red or Golden Lion, where I found him so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guised, that at first sight I hardly knew him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing I had been almost an hour in his company but the day before. After a little discourse, I made him acquainted with the whole Concern; who thereupon made answer, <hi>That he would see what could be done in it,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saying, <hi>There was a business on foot of far greater Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, which he hop'd would take effect.</hi> I desired to know what that business might be, he said, as best occurs to my present memory, <hi>That there were Endeavours using to procure that all the Arms, belonging to the Militia in</hi> London, <hi>should be brought and kept in a general Magazine, and then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61458:8"/> the City would be easily surpriz'd with Six thousand men, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Plot was discover'd.</hi> After a little more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, he asked me if I would go with him? To which I readily consented. Whereuppon we went to the <hi>Tower</hi> together; and being come to the Lord <hi>Arundel</hi>'s Lodgings, he desir'd me to tarry below for him (which I promis'd to do) till he went up. He had been there but a very short time, before there came forth a person, who, as I believe, was sent to give Intelligence to the Lords, of the said <hi>Churchill's</hi> being there: For upon the aforesaid Persons Return, I saw the Lord <hi>Petre,</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> with several other Persons go in where the said <hi>Churchill</hi> went in before.</p>
            <p>About an hour after that, <hi>Churchill</hi> came to me, and going back towards <hi>Knightsbridge,</hi> between <hi>Clarendon</hi> House and Hide Park, he bad me be of Courage, for there were great hopes, That all things would go well, for that the Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> had given him an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their great hopes, that the said Arms would be disposed of as aforesaid, and then the City should be surprized with six thousand men, and all disaffected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality, and interest should be disposed of as the Roman Catholicks pleased. I asked him how it was possible such a thing could be effected? He replyed, that the Popish Plot would in a little time be turned into a Presbyterian Plot, saying, there were Instruments at work to make the People believe, that the game of <hi>Forty one,</hi> was playing over again, and that there was a List taken of all the Names of those who were most forward in Prosecuting the Roman Catholicks: all which Persons he stigmatized by the name of <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> There was likewise another List of all the names of those who were reputed <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and had Considerable Estates; all which should be Confiscated, that thereby such
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61458:8"/> Sums of mony might be raised, that there might be no need of a Parliament, until such time as things were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter setled. I asked him whether he could help me into an Imployment? He said, he would go to the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> and discourse her Ladyship concerning me, and desir'd me to call in a day or two for an Answer. In this manner we parted for that time, and according to his desire I went about two days after to the aforesaid place at <hi>Knightsbridge,</hi> but found him altogether reserv'd and shie to let me know any thing more of his secresies, excusing himself, that he was just going into the Country, but would be glad to see me at his Return; which coldness of his was the reason that I never saw him since. For I believe the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> had rendr'd my Endeavors, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Captain <hi>Bedlow,</hi> as a design against them, which made him so extreamly caustious.</p>
            <p>About the same time, <hi>I</hi> became acquainted with one Mrs. <hi>Holbey, alias Brinknell</hi> (who in the following Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is often mentioned) much after the same manner as I did with Mr. <hi>Thompson.</hi> This Mrs. <hi>Holby</hi> I went to visit some time after Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> had detected the Sham <hi>Presbyterian Plot,</hi> and the contrivers thereof. Among the rest of our discourse, <hi>I</hi> told her, that the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> and others, who had imployed Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> were serv'd by him in their own kind. To which she reply'd, that I had been made use of, as to my former Proposals, had not there been a <hi>Presbyterian Plot</hi> upon discovery, so that <hi>I</hi> knew no more of their Transactions, as far as I can remember at present, until I became a Prisoner in the <hi>Marshalsey,</hi> which was in <hi>August</hi> 1680. I had not been in that Prison above three days, before one Mr. <hi>John Zeale,</hi> became likewise a Prisoner in the same place, who at the drinking of a Bowl of Punch, let some words fall, how he was like to become an Evidence in the Plot. I took little notice of his words then, until we were in Bed together, at what time I ask'd him how he was likely to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61458:9"/> become an Evidence in the Plot. He answered, That a certain person, whose name was <hi>Masson,</hi> a Victualler, living in the <hi>Strand,</hi> had endeavour'd to suborn him to swear High Treason against Sir <hi>Francis Ratcliff,</hi> whom formerly Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi> had served, in the nature of a Page; and how he was brought by the said <hi>Masson</hi> to Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> &amp; by him to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> For both the said Earl and the Dr. did at first really believe that <hi>Masson</hi> had brought a true and real Evidence to them. But his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, upon a strict Examination of Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> found that he knew nothing material of the business; and so <hi>Masson</hi> was lookt upon as a knave for his pains. For a further account of which, I refer the Reader to Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi>'s own Relation.</p>
            <p>Having heard Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi> declare thus much, I ask'd him whether he had any thing else of importance to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover? for that then I would send for some friends of mine to have them come, that he might be examined; to which he answer'd, he had.</p>
            <p>Next morning I writ a Letter, and sent it to Mrs. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> in which I acquainted her, that there was a person in the <hi>Marshalsey,</hi> that could make out several things of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance against the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> and <hi>Dr. Oates,</hi> which might prove advantagious to the Innocent. Withal I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd her to communicate the same to some friends, and let me have a speedy Answer. Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> came to me, and brought with her a Gentlewoman, who, as Mrs. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> told me, was Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> which afterwards I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood to be true by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> her self. I acquainted them, that there was a Gentleman, who was my Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, who could make a discovery against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and <hi>Dr. Oates.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> made answer, Let me have whatever he can say, under his own hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and when <hi>I</hi> see it, if it be of Consequence <hi>I</hi> will bring a Justice of the Peace or two, and have you both out to a Tavern to have <hi>Zeale</hi> Sworn. Upon which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61458:9"/> words of hers, <hi>I</hi> promised to perform her desire:</p>
            <p>At that time Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> brought two or three Books with her, Intituled <hi>Malice defeated,</hi> or the <hi>Mystery</hi> of the <hi>Meal-Tub;</hi> and while she stayed with us, she sent one of those Books by her Foot-boy, as <hi>I</hi> understood him to be, to a Justice of the Peace in <hi>Southwark,</hi> but at that time <hi>I</hi> neither knew the said Justice, nor could <hi>I</hi> remember his name for some time, though <hi>I</hi> had heard Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> &amp; her Friend make mention of it in the Room. But upon his coming to Examine Mr. <hi>Zeale, I</hi> begged leave to ask his Worship a Question, which he freely granted me, and promised to answer if he could. <hi>I</hi> then asked him, whether he could remember that a Boy came to him, with a Book from Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> and whether he refused it or no, saying to him, <hi>I</hi> believed it was an Idle Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet? To which he answered, that such a Boy did come to him, and brought him such a Book; but that he did not receive it.</p>
            <p>At the same time also, for a farther encouragement Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> gave me a Crown-piece to drink a glass of Wine with Mr. <hi>Zeale,</hi> assuring me, if he had anything material to discover, we should not tarry in Prison long; and so she departed, leaving one of the aforesaid Books for us to peruse, saying, it was a Book that would Instruct us how we should not Err, or words to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; whereupon both Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> took their leaves, and went away.</p>
            <p>The next Morning early, <hi>I</hi> borrowed a Pen and Ink, and after <hi>I</hi> had done with it, <hi>I</hi> laid it in the window of my Chamber, and going out of the Room, <hi>I</hi> saw the said <hi>Zeale</hi> rise out of his bed in his shirt, and make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the window. When <hi>I</hi> came into the room again, I found him in bed, where I heard a noise like the folding of paper, which <hi>I</hi> then did not much regard: but in a little tsme after the said <hi>Zaile</hi> was up, shewed he me a Paper, saying, Here are the Heads which I have kept by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61458:10"/> me, and what I can swear against the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oates;</hi> when <hi>I</hi> had viewed it, and read it, <hi>I</hi> told him; <hi>If this be all, it will a vail nothing.</hi> Then Recollecting my self that the noise of the folding of paper about the bed was made by Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> and that the Paper was very clean, and the words but newly written, (which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards confessed to be true) he then told me he had more to declare, but was loth to trust me, being a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. However at length with much persuation, <hi>I</hi> got him to write a second Paper. Which he had no sooner finished, but in came Mrs <hi>Cellier</hi> into my Room, and Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> at my request went out. Presently <hi>I</hi> shewed her the aforesaid Paper, which after she had taken and read, she told me, she would go into the Barrough, and shew it to a Friend that tarryed for her. With that she went avvay, and in an hour; time return'd again, and then desired me to transcribe a certain Paper vvhich she had brought back along vvith her; but vvhich vvas not of Mr. <hi>Zeals</hi> hand vvriting, and to vvhich much more had been added than vvas in the paper, vvhich she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from me, and carryed out along, vvith her a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before; at her request <hi>I</hi> did transcribe it, but took no notice to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> perceived the matter to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd.</p>
            <p>When <hi>I</hi> had done, she desir'd me to get <hi>Zeale</hi> to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it; telling me that the next morning, Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> should come for it; vvithal giving me this caution, to take no notice to Mrs. <hi>Holbey,</hi> that the said Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> had been vvith me.</p>
            <p>Accordingly <hi>Zeal</hi> did Transcribe the said enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged paper, and Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> came and received the same, and at the same time made great promises of a very large gratuity to Mr. <hi>Zeal.</hi> After vvhich, she desir'd him the said Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> to put his hand to some other Paper; vvhich he accordingly did; vvhich being done, Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> vvent avvay, telling me she would go to Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> vvith the said Papers.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61458:10"/>
            <p>After this Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> coming to me to the Prison, I desired him to go to Mrs. <hi>Holbey,</hi> to know how the business succeeded; which accordingly he did, and was by Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> upon that Accompt brought to Mrs. <hi>Cellyers,</hi> and so returning back, he brought me another Paper, containing in it more than that which I had given to Mrs. <hi>Cellyer</hi> before. Upon the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, said Mr. <hi>Dalton Mrs. Cellyers desires to have this Paper also transcribed by</hi> Mr Zeal, <hi>and I will call the next Morning for it.</hi> When Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> was gon, I shewed it to <hi>Zeal,</hi> telling him, that there was more in that Paper than was in the former; and ask'd him, whether he could Swear to it? To which <hi>Zeal</hi> replied, <hi>I can, for ought they know.</hi> Whereupon I told him, that I could not believe Mrs. <hi>Cellyer</hi> had been such a Woman. Upon these Words, Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> came close to the point, and told me, that if I would be faithful to him, he would be true to me, and we will agree to try what this Woman would be at. To which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented. Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> according to his promise, called the next morning, and had the Paper transcribed to his desire, by <hi>Zeal.</hi> Away he went with it, but in less than an hour return'd with it again, because it was not Sign'd; whereupon <hi>Zeal</hi> did likewise Signe it and gave it to <hi>Dalton</hi> to carry to <hi>Cellyer.</hi> She upon sight of the Paper which <hi>Dalton</hi> earried her, ask'd him, as he told me, for the Original, which he left with <hi>Zeal</hi> and me. Whereupon he came back the same day, and told us, he must have it; and gave us for his Reason, for that <hi>Mrs. Cellyer</hi> said, she would not have the hand writing seen by any means, in regard it was well known by most persons of Quality at Court.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> at first was very loath to part with it; however, I thought it not convenient at that time to disobliege her; and therefore over perswaded Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> to give it the said <hi>Dalton.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61458:11"/>
            <p>Upon the delivery of the Paper, Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> told the said <hi>Dalton,</hi> that if he parted with the said Paper, he should not know what to swear to; for that he had no Copy of the same, and therefore he desired to have a Copy in another hand sent by Mrs. <hi>Holbey.</hi> To which Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> made Answer that it was torn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it wos sound to be impertinent. In the mean time I found by <hi>Zeal,</hi> That he mistrusted all this to be a contrivance of mine: upon which I promised him he should be fully satisfied to the contrary, if he could propose any way to effect the same, whereby such a satisfaction might be brought to pass.</p>
            <p>Thereupon we consulted both together, and at length agreed, That when Mrs. <hi>Celyer</hi> came again, Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> should get into a little Colehole adjoining to the Chamber where we lay, and from whence he might hear all the Discourse which should pass be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and my self.</p>
            <p>In a very short time after, Mrs <hi>Celyers</hi> came again, and then in the first place gave me many thanks for my Care and Diligence in the Business; urging what great Distress the Roman-Catholicks were in, saying, that his Majesty was resolved to have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of them, and further adding, that it was better to die by endeavouring to advantage their Cause, than to die or be utterly ruined by lying still, with some more Discourse to the same purpose; end so promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to come again in a day or two, she took her leave and went away.</p>
            <p>When she was gon, <hi>Zeal</hi> accused me for not being as good as my promise. To which I answered, that she came unexpected, and therefore could not find any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to get him where we agreed, assuring him withal, that she was suddenly to come again.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61458:11"/>
            <p>Soon after Mrs. <hi>Celyers</hi> did come again according to her Promise, and I gave <hi>Zeal</hi> the Sign by laying my Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to my Nose; and the opportunity by holding her in the Yard in Discourse, until I Judged he was got into the Cole-hole. When I thought him hid, I brought her into my Chamber, where we had this following Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the best of what I can possibly at present re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Cell. Mr. Lewis,</hi> are you resolved to do your self and all the Roman Catholicks in <hi>England</hi> good?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis.</hi> Yes, If I can with safety. Then she look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every way about the Room, and under the Bed with a careful Eye, and then not believing any body within hearing, she sate down and went on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cell.</hi> I understand you can do any thing with Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> pray let me desire you to ask him what Ship his Father is Purser of, and likewise know of him what number of Ships there may be where the Ship to which his Father belongs doth lye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis.</hi> Madam, I will give you the best satisfaction I can.</p>
            <p>With that I went out of the Room, pretending to go to <hi>Zeal,</hi> who was then really in the Cole-hole, and having staid some time without, I brought her word the Ship was called the <hi>Princess,</hi> as I formerly had written to Mrs. <hi>Holbey;</hi> and told her moreover, that the Ship lay at <hi>Chatham;</hi> where there Rode almost half the Navy. Upon that she again repeated to me the miserable Condition in which the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks were, and how that it was not possible to live more miserable under any Prince in Christendome than they were like to do under this King.</p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> said Mrs. <hi>Celier,</hi> if you will after I have procured your Liberty, go with Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> and set the Ship to which his Father belongs on Fire, and as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61458:12"/> many more as you can. I will give you fifty pounds to effect the same, and I will make that fifty three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, after the business is accomplished; and there shall be the like Order taken for the rest in other Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. And to this purpose, when you are out, I will bring you to those persons who shall engage for what I have promised you; and they shall give you your Instructions how to proceed, and dispatches shall be sent into <hi>France,</hi> to be in a readiness to give Assistance. To which I replied, Madam, why will you impart such a secret as this to me? especially before you have the Answers to those dispatches?</p>
            <p>You are very curious, said she, but for your satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, there are Answers come already for ought you know.</p>
            <p>I replied, can there be no better way, than to set the Fleet on Fire? To which she answered, there was not. For said she, we have tried all other ways we can think of. Then falling into other Discourse, she discovered what great hopes the Roman-Catholicks had, when Sir <hi>Robert Payton</hi> was committed to the Tower, That he would have impeacht the <hi>Rotten Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament,</hi> meaning those that were disaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Roman-Catholicks, and particularising the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> that so they might have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Tower; expecting that when they were so committed, the People in general would have been glad that an Act of Indempnity should have passed, by which means the Lords in the Tower, and all others concern'd in the Plot should be discharg'd without exceptions.</p>
            <p>She further also said, she was to receive in four or five days time, a considerable sum of mony from the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> but for what use I cannot tell, out of which sum I should have my three hundred pounds for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61458:12"/> burning the ships, saying, she would take speedy care to have both me and <hi>Zeal</hi> suddenly out of Prison; in Confirmation whereof she then gave me a broad piece of Gold, took her leave and went away.</p>
            <p>In some short time after, Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> came by <hi>Mrs. Cellyers</hi> direction, to take Copies of our Actions, which then could be no less then a hundred and twenty pounds, in Order to have us discharged, but the next News I heard was that <hi>Mrs. Cellyer</hi> was not only in Prison, but Convicted for Printing her Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet. Thereupon not hearing from her, as I was wont to do, I intreated Mr. <hi>Dalton</hi> to go see her, which he accordingly did; and as he told Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> and my self, she desired him to encourage Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> and I was not to flinch, for she hoped that all things would go well, notwithstanding the hard measures she had; for that she doubted not, but they who put her upon Publishing the said Book, would stand by her.</p>
            <p>In some short time after, <hi>Dalton</hi> went to see <hi>Mrs. Holbey,</hi> who as he said, delivered him a Letter, which she had received from <hi>Cellyers,</hi> after her Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Newgate,</hi> directed to Captain <hi>Hill</hi> a Prisoner in the Fleet, <hi>Holbey,</hi> desiring him to go with the said Letter to <hi>Hill,</hi> which he promised to do; but before he went with it, he brought it to me, telling me withal how he came by it, thereupon I opened it, and found the Contents thereof to be to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to the best of my Remembrance.</p>
            <p>Sir, Pray let me know how much it will cost to remove two poor Gentlemen from the Marshalsey to your Prison. They are to become Evidences alike with you, keep them steady; for I hope all things will go well very speedily, Subscribed <hi>E. Cellyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After I had Read it, I sealed it up, and Mr <hi>Dalton</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:61458:13"/> went with it, he being gone, I made <hi>Zeal</hi> acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the said Letter, whereupon he writ to <hi>Hill,</hi> being formerly acquainted with him, to let him know how he was suspected by the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and therefore desired him to satisfie them better concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. Which I believe the said <hi>Hill</hi> did do; for soon after, came two Women from <hi>Hill,</hi> and from the <hi>Sun Eclipst,</hi> though not so much <hi>Clouded,</hi> but that they hoped he would Shine again, (under which Denomination Mrs. <hi>Celiers</hi> often sent to us) and brought with them a Letter from <hi>Hill,</hi> to desire <hi>Zeal</hi> to send him by them in writing, the particulars of what he had to swear, which <hi>Zeal</hi> promised to do, and had done it, but that he was by me disswaded from it. One of the said Women told me why <hi>Zeal</hi> had not Money sent him, in particular, was because he was not sworn, upon which one of the said Women took an occasion to ask him, whether he would be sworn? For that then they would get some Justices to come to him; to which Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> seemed unwilling, saying, he was to go before the King and Council, where he was to be put to his Oath, which would be much beter.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Mrs- Celiers</hi> having formerly ordered me to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune <hi>Mrs- Holbey,</hi> by Letters for Money, because as she said, she would not have her to know any thing of the Concern (but since I rather, believe by that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, she intended to have something to produce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us, in case we should Confess any thing against her) I writ a Letter to Mrs. <hi>Holbey</hi> according to my order, to desire her to speak to the <hi>Sun Eclipst,</hi> to lend me some Money towards my inlargement and then I would follow the business, and get other Evidences to Confirm Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> or to that effect; but really intending by that means, to discover more of their designs, if possible, to make things more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61458:13"/>
            <p>Soon after the sending of that Letter, Mrs. <hi>Holbey,</hi> on a Saturday in the Evening, came and sent for me to the Under Clerks House of this Prison, where I went, and found her in Company with an other Woman. <hi>Mrs. Holbey</hi> told me, she had shewn my Letter to the <hi>Sun Eclipst,</hi> &amp;c. saying, the <hi>Sun Eclipst,</hi> meaning <hi>Mrs. Celiers,</hi> desired me to have patience for three weeks or a Month longer, by which time we should both be certainly discharged, adding fatther that the Reason why I was not Released sooner, was, because the <hi>Sun Eclipst</hi> did not Judge <hi>Zeal</hi> wise e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to manage the business against the Lord <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and Doctor <hi>Oats,</hi> and they were resolved to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease neither of us until <hi>Zeal</hi> was sworn.</p>
            <p>Now the substance of the so often mentioned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, relating to the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Oats,</hi> and so often Corrected and Advised by <hi>Mrs. Celyer,</hi> and intended for a Deposition was, that the Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> had subornd <hi>Zeal</hi> to swear high Treason against the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Peterborough,</hi> and that Docter <hi>Oats</hi> had suborn'd him to swear high Treason against Sir <hi>Francis Ratcliff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I had delivered the foregoing Information to the Right Honourable the House of Commons, I was ordered up into the Speakers Chamber; and Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Stringer</hi> and Collonel <hi>Warcup,</hi> another of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Justices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Middlesex</hi> and Liberties of <hi>Westminster,</hi> took my Affidavit upon Oath, of the Truth of what was therein contained. And being then demanded by the said Justices of the Peace, whether or no I knew what Justices of the Peace they were, proposed by Mrs. <hi>Celier</hi> to take Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi>'s Examination. I made them Answer, that I would tell them all that I could remember concerning the Business. Upon that, I was remanded back again
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61458:14"/> to the Bar of the House of Commons a second time, where I made this farther Information by word of Mouth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That when <hi>Mrs. Celier</hi> came to me to the <hi>Marshal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sea,</hi> she entered into a debate, in what manner, and by what persons, as fittest for the purpose, it would be most proper to get Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> examin'd. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, I delivered my Opinion to her, that it would be the most convenient way to have the said Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> over the Water, to the Lord Chief <hi>Justice Scroggs,</hi> who as I understood by the Roman Catholicks was their friend. But Mr. <hi>Celier</hi> would by no means yield to that, alledging for her reason, that if he should take the Examination, it would come to be known, which might probably render him uncapable to do the Roman Catholicks any farther good services. Then I judg'd that the Recorder of <hi>London</hi> Sir <hi>George J<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fferies</hi> would be a proper person. To which she answered to the same effect, as she had done before in reference to the Lord Chief Justiee: and then concluded her self, that Mr. <hi>Foster</hi> and Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey,</hi> both in Commission of the Peace for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Surrey,</hi> would be the most proper persons for that purpose, and that she would have them come and take the said <hi>Zeals</hi> Examination. But they did not come, in regard that I disswaded her from it. Alledging that it would be better to have him first discharged, for that otherwise the whole business would look with such a face, as if what he did, were the effects of his necessity, and to procure his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>I further inform'd the Right Honourable House, that I had a Brother who was a Menial Servant in the Portugal Embassadors House, that ilv'd then in Great Queen-street, and that the acquaintance which I had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61458:14"/> with others of the Family, call'd me often thither, by which means I knew the said Embassador personally. That I did see the said Embassador go into the House of the Lord Chief Justice <hi>Scroggs</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> But what His Excellencies business was, I know not, nor any other particulars in any kind whatsoever, against the said Lord Chief Justice, but onely what I have already declared, and that I had heard many <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks</hi> esteem and speak of him as their Friend.</p>
            <p>I must acknowledge that I never receiv'd a greater inward satisfaction from any thing that ever I did, than when by disburthening my Conscience of that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Load that lay upon it, I had made this full Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of what I knew. The apprehension of Crimes which I had consented to, and undertaken to carry on, so horrid in the Contrivance, and so dreadful in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, did so strangely disturb and disquiet my thoughts, that the more I endeavour'd to struggle with those apprehensions, and throw off their uneasie weight from my mind, the more I saw my self entangl'd in those fears and jealousies, to which a Design of wicked craft and contrivance, and the dangerous consequences thereof had expos'd me.</p>
            <p>This put me into a deep Consultation with my self, what course to take. Among all the ways I could propose to my self, none seem'd so honest nor so safe, as that of a full Discovery. To this purpose my first thoughts directed me to throw my self at the feet of the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> as being a person whose Life was so much aimed at in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance I had to reveal. But then I found that my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment deny'd me the Opportunity of personal Address. For remedy of which misfortune, I wrote a Letter to a Relation of my own, to the effect as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61458:15"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>It has bin my misfortune, or rather good luck, to become a Prisoner to this place, where I have bin made acquainted with some horrid Designs, which are now on foot against the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and against the never to be forgotten Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> against whom there is a Paper containing horrid and most false Articles to be deliver'd into Council, on purpose to destroy his Lordship. Therefore I desire you to come to me, and bring a friend with you, in whom you can confide, and I will declare all to you, and make it appear as clear as the day, or never desire to be own'd by you, as</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your most humble Servant<lb/> and Kinsman,</hi>
                        <lb/> W. LEWIS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter (the Lady not being at home to whom it was directed) was brought back again to me. So that being at a stand what to do, I resolv'd to take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a Gentleman, who was also a Prisoner in the same House for Debt, who, we observ'd, had long had a jealousie of our proceedings, and had pry'd all he could into our Actions, but all to no purpose, till I made him privy to my Design of Discovery. He being one that had bin formerly in Publick Employment, and by that means a person that had had the Honour to be known to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> undertook to send to his Lordship the Letter which I had written to my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation;</hi> which the said Gentleman did accordingly, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closing the same in a Letter of his own directed to his Lordship, in these words:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61458:15"/>
                  <head>Superscribed, to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it please your Lordship,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I did in my first Information which I presented to your Lordship, give a Character of Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs that were on foot by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> against your Lordship's Person. I have so far prevailed upon Mr. <hi>Lewis,</hi> as now to make a full Discovery of all their Transactions, and have brought him to give it under his hand, which he hath done in a Letter to one Mrs. <hi>Ingram,</hi> which Letter I have here enclosed sent to your Lordship, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Subscribed,<lb/>
                     <salute>May it please your Lordship,</salute>
                     <signed>your<lb/> Lordships most humble Servant,<lb/>
                        <hi>JOHN HAYTER.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon the receipt of those Letters, the next morning two Gentlemen came to me from his Lordship, as I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards understood, to the Prison, desiring to know what it was I had to say? Further adding, That if I were not willing to disclose the particulars to them, they would, if I thought fitting, bring some Justices of the Peace to the Prison, to take my Examination. To which I readily consented. Thereupon the said two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, took their leaves for that time, and in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon of the same day returned again with two of His Majesties Justices of the Peace for the Country of <hi>Surrey, viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Richard How,</hi> and <hi>Peter Rich</hi> Esq;, both Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament. The first of these took the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of one Mr. <hi>Hayter,</hi> the Gentleman before mention'd, who had had so long a jealousie of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61458:16"/> touching several dangerous words that he had heard Mr. <hi>John Zeale</hi> utter at several times against some Persons of great Honour.</p>
            <p>Then both the said Justices of the Peace took my Examination relating only to Mrs. <hi>Celliers,</hi> the Popish Midwife, because it was very late, and I did not think fit to disclose any more at that time, believing it most convenient to discover the secret of burning His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Fleet in the first place, not knowing how soon it might be attempted by others, who, as Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> had told me, were to be engag'd in the same Design, though they were unknown to me.</p>
            <p>In short time after this, I was sent for to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, where I gave my Information to the same effect, as I had given it before to the two said Justices of the Peace. Which <hi>I</hi> had no sooner done, but Mr. <hi>Peter Rich</hi> was called for in, and there delivered my Information in writing taken before him and Sir <hi>Richard How.</hi> Which being read, <hi>I</hi> was order'd to withdraw, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded back to Prison.</p>
            <p>Soon after, <hi>I</hi> was order'd to attend the Lords of the Secret Committee, in the Lord Privy Seal's Chamber, near by the Lords House, where <hi>I</hi> was further examin'd, and so remanded, but heard no more of the business in seven or eight days.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, one night, as Mr. <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>I</hi> were a-bed together, <hi>I</hi> told him <hi>I</hi> had something of great Consequence to say against the <hi>Lord Arundell,</hi> but was resolv'd not to declare it till <hi>I</hi> was brought before the House of Commons, which I daily expected; and wondring I was not sent for by them in all that time, which was about three weeks time from my first Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61458:16"/> A thing that very much perplex'd me, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the great guilt under which I lay for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the Treason so long, and not having my Pardon.</p>
            <p>Upon which Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> the next day, as I afterwards understood, sent to Mr. <hi>Rich,</hi> before mentioned, to intreat him with all speed to come to him: Which he accordingly did; to whom the said Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> then disclosed what I had told him the night before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lord <hi>Arundel;</hi> all which was done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge.</p>
            <p>Upon which a Messenger came, and acquainted me, that Mr. <hi>Rich</hi> would speak with me in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. I presently waited upon him: (Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> the Keeper being then in the Room with him) But when I understood the business, I was not a little surpriz'd at Mr. <hi>Rich</hi>'s Question, finding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by how Mr. <hi>Zeal</hi> had dealt by me. However Mr. <hi>Rich</hi> ask'd me, whether I were willing to declare my whole knowledge to him? Which I was really un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to do, and beg'd his pardon for such my unwillingness. Who thereupon desired me to tell him the name of the Lord, against whom, as I had intimated to Mr. <hi>Zeal,</hi> I had something to say. Upon which I nam'd the Lord <hi>Arundel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next morning early, being the 12. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> I wrote a Letter to the said Mr. <hi>Rich,</hi> desiring him not to harbour any ill Opinion of me; for that the reason I refus'd to be examin'd the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by him, was not out of any disrespect, or distrust of him, but by reason I would not have the secret divulg'd, there being then another Person in the Room.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:61458:17"/>
            <p>The same Morning I received an Answer from him, that he would harbour no ill Opinion of me; telling me that he would be with me in the Afternoon, and advising me to be ready to discover the whole Truth of what I knew.</p>
            <p>In the mean time came a Messenger from the House of Lords, with an Order for me to be immediately brought before the House. Where, at the Bar, I acquainted their Lordships that I was surpriz'd, not expecting to be call'd to any Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before the Afternoon: However if their Lordships commanded to do it, I would deliver it in the best manner that I could remember, which should be nothing but the Truth; which was then done in reference to the Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> referring my self for the rest to my Examination taken by the aforesaid Justices of the Peace.</p>
            <p>Upon that I was ordered to withdraw; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after, I again gave the same Information, relating to the Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> before Sir <hi>Timothy Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Warcup.</hi> This was upon a <hi>Saturday;</hi> and the next <hi>Munday</hi> I was order'd to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend again by ten of Clock: Which I did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, at the Bar of the House; where while I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, the Information aforesaid, taken by the three Justices of the Peace before mentioned, was read to me: The Earl of <hi>Radnor</hi> at the same time asking me, whither I did own that Information or no, by Vertue of the Oath which had been already given me by the said House? To which I answered in the Affirmative. And so was remanded, and heard no more of the business, nor of my Pardon till three or four days after. At what time I was hurried out
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61458:17"/> of my Bed, by vertue of a Rule of the Court of Kings Bench, to give Evidence to the Grand Jury against Mrs. <hi>Cellier;</hi> which I did that morning.</p>
            <p>Which being done, and being very apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive of the danger I was in, I made my Address to <hi>John Arnold</hi> Esq; now a Member of the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able House, representing my condition to him, how it had been above three Weeks since my first Discovery, and that I could not be heard before the House: Whereupon he went and acquainted some of the Members with what I had said. The Effect whereof was, that in less than an hours time I was called to the Bar of the House of Commons, where I first delivered my Information by word of Mouth, and then in Writing, as I have in these Sheets declared and published the same.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>